<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Complaynt of the soule</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1519</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5609</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844719</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9557</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9557)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 32:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Complaynt of the soule</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In flete strete at the sygne of the sonne, by Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1519?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A B⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Soul --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9557:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9557:1"/>
            <p>¶ Complaynt of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </q>
                  <q>Heu infame.</q>
                  <q>Furore conſumor.</q>
                  <q>Spes nobis nulla</q>
                  <q>Animam ami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>mus.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9557:2"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth a lamentable complay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule maketh of the wretched lyfe of the body.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Edet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vite me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. ¶ My ſoule is we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the lyfe. For there I ſee no thynge but mater of ſorowe myſerye &amp; ſynne. The parte of my lyfe paſſed is ful lamentable wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membre it / the preſent parte ſuppreſſed myn herte with heuyneſſe for it is vnreformed. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grete loſſe of vertue in theſe two partes &amp; abhomynacyon of ſynne putteth me in gret fere of the thyrde parte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is to come. And yf my lyfe myght be prolonged ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres only in vertuous vſes / yet it myght not recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pence for the manyfolde offences whiche I haue done in the preſent ſyghte of my lorde god and terryble Iuge of my lyfe whiche hateth no thynge but only ſynne. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las than my ſoule may be ful of ſorowe whiche hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoked my lorde god / my mooſt tender louer to be wroth with me and to hate me more than I do a dog or a ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge carayne / for no thynge is ſo vyle ſo lothſome ſo ſtynkynge nor ſo abhomynable in the ſyght or ſmellyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of man / as ſynne in the ſyght or ſmellynge of god. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las alas that I ſholde offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de my lorde god whiche hath made me of nought &amp; where he myght haue made me a ſtone or an vnreaſonable beeſt / he hath made me to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage of hymſelfe a reaſonable creature / and whan I was loſte redemed me with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precyous blood of his her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and ſuffred the mooſt bytterſt deth for me / an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in an my lyfe he hath ſhewed grete kyndeneſſe vnto nie / and I haue ſhewed grete vnky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e agayen to hym / he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me &amp; I not hym / for I wyll not do after the wyll of hym / but I ſette my wyl afore his wyll / and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:9557:2"/> of myſelfe afore the pleaſure of hym / and in fulfyllynge my wyl I care not to dyſpleaſe hym. And thus I ſe not by hym whiche hath made ſo moche of me he hath made heuen and erthe for me / and hath comen to this erth to teche me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of ſaluacyon / and hath ordeyned for me yf I wolde loue hym the meſtymable Ioye of his deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte and to receyue the eternall kyngedome of felycyte ¶ All theſe thynges I forgete / &amp; I ordre myſelfe by my lewde neglygence and vnhappy lyuynge to leſe the loue of my lorde god / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſcendynge Ioye of his kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. I ordre me by my wretched lyfe to euerlaſtynge payne / woo I be a veſſell of deth of Ire and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngnacyon of god / he hath made my ſoule by the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of baptyme a veſſell of mercy and grace / and I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue defouled it with abhomynable ſynne / &amp; made it with out his Inmeſurable mercy veſſell of dampnacyon to be brente in the fyre of hell amonge the horryble fendes euer without endynge. ¶ Alas what ſhall I do what ſhall I ſaye whiche haue erred thus ferre out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way of vertue and is caſted depe in to the pytte of ſynne. A grete cauſe I haue of lamentacyon whiche am in this grete Ieoperdye of endleſſe dampnacyon. I am a waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a dyſtroyer of my ſoule and body. I deſtroye the goodes of nature / of grace / and of the worlde as a man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is worſe than good in the ſyght of hym the whiche hath gyuen them to me to the entent that I ſholde vſe them vertuouſly. And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyghte of hym whiche ſhall mooſt bytterly punyſſhe hym. I vſe them vycyouſly I am clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> derke cloudes of Ignoraunce / and reprouable neglygence of my lorde g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d / of myſelfe and of vertuouſe lyuynge. All my lyfe is ſynfull / &amp; as a drye tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e barayne and ferre from all fruyte of vertue I thynke not on the
<pb facs="tcp:9557:3"/> dredfull Iugement of god / where I ſhall ſtande afore the terryble Iugement of cryſt / and to rendre accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te for all the dydes that I haue done in my ſoule and in my body. O there I ſhall ſhewe an vnfruytful lyfe / and yf there be ony fruyte therin it is but fayned and falſe / or vnperfyte or corrupted and other it is full lytell plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or elles vtterly dyſpleaſed god. And notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge that euery man there ſhall be fedde after this lyfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuche fruyte as that he hath brought ſorth in this lyfe / than my fedynge is lyke to be full bytter vnto me. ¶ O how ſorowful I ought than to be / for except y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſorowe for my ſynne in this lyfe. I am lyke for to be brought to grete ſorowe after this lyfe. ¶ O my ſynful ſoule. O my myſerable ſoule loke vpon thy ſelfe / ſee how thou arte brought in to the grete derkeneſſe of ſynne ſo depe that thou canſte not ſee thy ſelfe. Seeſt thou not how y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in to vayne thoughtes &amp; vnlefull deſyres. ¶ Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre that al the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou lokeſt not vpon vertue is loſt and thou ſhalt be ſhent therfore / as moche tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leſeſt than whiche myght tourne the to grete Ioye in tyme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge / and now all ſhall tourne the to grete punyſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment except thou lerne to amende and to ſpende the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydue of thy tyme. O howe aferde thou ſholdeſt be to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue an vnfruytful lyfe / for the vnfruytful lyfe is a damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable lyfe as almyȝty god whiche is very trouth ſayth Euery tree whiche bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth not forth good fruyte it ſhal be cutte downe &amp; caſte in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre. ¶ A mercy god what ſhal I do than for I am ſo barayne ſo drye frome all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocyon and moyſture of contrycyon and grace that I am deapte and redye to the fyre. ¶ A mercyfull lorde cutte me not downe by deth to ſuche tyme that my tree maye haue moyſture thrugh thy grace &amp; brynge forthe
<pb facs="tcp:9557:3"/> ſome profytable fruytes of penaunce / all my dydes that I do arte not ſuffycyent to recompence for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mete and drynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I receyue of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> to my bodely ſuſtenaunce. ¶ A where with ſhal I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recompence for my ſoule / my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / my wytte / my herynge / my ſeynge / my ſpeche / my helth / my bodely power / my lyfe / and where w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all ſhall I recompence for my ſynne / &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loſſe of grace whiche paſſeth theſe all / for none ſhall be brought to dampnacy on but ſuche as for lacke of grace are defouled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſynne who ſo ſpendeth more in fedynge of a beeſt tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the in themſelfe is not that ſuperfluous expence and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proufytable. And yet mercyful lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nouryſſheſt day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and haboundantly an vnproufytable worme &amp; ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge ſynner. ¶ A good lorde thou woldeſt not that this wretche ſhall peryſſhe of whome thou dooſt ſo large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and ſo tenderly kepeſt it. Many good thou gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt it vnaſked / &amp; frome many euyll thynges he preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it vnthanked of it / thou kepeſt me / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ledeſt me / and protecteſt me frome many perylles / and as an vnkynde wretche I remembre not this &amp; I do not calle in welth to the but in grete ſorowe &amp; fere whan than that I am lyke to falle. ¶ A good lorde a more or a greter wretche is there none in this worlde than I am / and a mooſt vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynde katyf / a wretche / a worme / a veſſell full of vnclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and abhomynacyon not worthy for to be called a man or a reaſonable creature For I abuſe that reaſon / that memorye / and that fredome of wyll whiche thou haſte gyuen vnto me with all the gyftes &amp; all the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetes of nature and of fortune / and ſo I am wors than a beeſt the whiche hath not the helpes and haue no reaſon for to dyrecte theyr lyfe to the honoure and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe of god as I haue / they haue no fredome of wyll
<pb facs="tcp:9557:4"/> for to choſe the good &amp; to leue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euyl as I haue. My rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is gyuen to me for to knowe my lorde god / &amp; for to knowe how I ſholde lyue to the pleaſure of hym and to thynke vpon y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyfe that is to come / &amp; holyly for to ordre myſefe therto / and for to auoyde the grete tourmentes and the endleſſe trybulacyon the whiche after this lyfe is ordeyned for ſynne. ¶ A god mercy what grete der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe am I in / and my ſoule is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maner made blynde y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> gooſtely ſyghte is gone. I loke not vp to my lord god with the ſyght of my ſoule / but all my thought / all my memorye / all my loue / and all the grete pleaſure in my ſoule is downe warde / &amp; all is to vanytees of this erthe I am erthly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my prayers / in me ſtudye / in my labours in my medytacyons / and in all my conuerſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I may well thynke that theſe wordes are verefyed of me. The prophete Y ſaye ſayth. Erthe erthe erthe here y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worde of god / for I am made of erthe / and haſtely I ſhall tourne to erthe / and al my conuerſacyon is but erthe. I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted good lorde in the ſyght of the after my loue / yf I loue erthe I am erthe / yf I loue erthly thynges I am erthly / yf I loue gooſtly thynges I am gooſtly / and yf I loue the good lorde whiche arte very god than I am godly. ¶ A good lorde I fere than that I am i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon but as vyle erthe. For in the erthe and in the erth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thynges is euer my mynde. I kepe it not vpon the good lorde / ne vpon y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy orderynge of my ſoule I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſuffred my ſelfe by wretched cuſtome ſo longe and ſo contynually for to renne frome the and frome actuall thoughtes of my ſoule and thynges whiche are prouffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for to promote my ſoule in vertue and in good wer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. Than nowe I can not without grete payne and without grete laboure for to fyxe my mynde ony tyme
<pb facs="tcp:9557:4"/> or ſpace vpon the or vpon the holy dyreccyon and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of my ſoule / and I of a frowarde and of an obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate wyll in wretchednes enforces not neyther care not myſelfe for to take parte agaynſt this myſerable Incly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon of myſelfe / and ſo it goeth al downewarde with me. I come not vpwarde to the neyther I wyll not gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely applye myſelfe for to come to the by actuall medyta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon and by parfyte loue of the. I ſlepe. I dreme and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I ſhall fynde whan the ſharpe paynes of dethe ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me for to open the eye of my ſoule / for than I ſhall clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſe how vaynely and how ſynfully and how wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and how vnhappy and how myſerably and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracyouſly that I haue myſpended the tyme of this ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whiche tyme is gyuen vnto me onely bycauſe that I ſholde ſpende it fruytfully in good and in vertuouſe lyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge vnto the grete honour and to the grete worſhyp of our ſauyour Cryſt Iheſu and vnto the promocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my ſoule in the glorye of eternall lyfe and of the heuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly felycyte / and alſo for to auoyde eternall dampnacyon whiche is ordeyned by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ryghtwyſneſſe of almyȝty god to the Inordynate lyuers of this lyfe / the whiche conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the goodes that they haue receyned of god to theyr eternall reproue / ſorowe and / payne: &amp; for to receyue of almyghty god fynally perpetuall dampnacyon.</p>
            <p>VEdet animam meam vite mee. ¶ I am wery of my lyfe. It is ſo full of Ignoraunce and of nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence / ſo ful of vnhappy deſyres and of ſynful wordes ſo full of forgetfulneſſe and ſo full of euyll thoughtes / &amp; ſo full of vnfruytful dydes and werkes and ſo full of vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prouffytable heuyneſſe / and ſo ful vnlawful ſaddeneſſe and ſo full of vayne Ioyes and ſynfull dylectacyons
<pb facs="tcp:9557:5"/> with foule wretched and myſerable pleaſures / alſo it is full of paynes with vnpacyence of proude deſyres and with a ful couetous mynde / &amp; with al theſe myſeryes I ſee how y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> my ſelf is but a courſe &amp; a rennynge to dethe / and now I am more nerer it than whan as I laſte ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of it. The deth cometh ſhortely / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe gooth awaye full faſtely and full ſwyftely / &amp; at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> houre of deth I am lyke to be called for to rendre accomptes of my lyfe / and I am vnprouyded and vnware for to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente the Iuge of my lyfe / and than I ſhall be mooſt full of ſorowe and payne &amp; lamente or complayne the tyme y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> euer I came in to this lyfe / whiche ſo neclyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly hath loſte the profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of this. A good lorde I am aſhamed &amp; abaſſhed of my lyfe in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſyghte of the good lorde whiche all thynge ſeth clerly / &amp; nothynge maye be hydde frome the. ¶ Sythen it is ſo that ſhame is feere of rebuke and reproue / and there is no rebuke whiche that I drede ſo moche as I do the rebuke of the good lorde / wherfore I am mooſt aſhamed of my ſynful lyfe in the ſyghte of the / and thus I am aſhamed to lyue / and yet I am aferde to dye. For yf I may auoyde by the grete mercy of god the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of eternall dampnacyon / yet I fere y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I ſhall bere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me in to purgatory the gylte of many ſynnes / &amp; I ſhall paye by grete payne / the duyte of many oblygacyons / grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me good lorde perfyte fere of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. For whan I ſhall not fere by deth to come to the / for thy fere maketh ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to declyne and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee frome ſynne. ¶ A good lorde yf I had thy fere perfytly I ſholde be more a dredde ony thynge to thynke or to deſyre ſynfully in the ſyght of the / than I am to do ſynne in the ſyght of man. The ſynfull mocyons of my mynde are ſo abhomynable in the beholdynge of the as the dyde of ſhamefull ſynne in
<pb facs="tcp:9557:5"/> the ſyght of man than yf I fered y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I ſholde be apunyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and aſhamed to thynke ony thynge dyſpleaſynge to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. I waute theſe fere of the / and why / for I haue not perfyte fayth of the. A than I am vnfaythful / and with out fayth no man maye pleaſe the / and thus all my lyfe is dyſpleaſynge vnto the. ¶ A good lorde what ſhall I do for I want fayth of the / fere of the / loue of the / &amp; dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the / but I want not the drede of the worlde / loue of the worlde / and ſhame of the worlde. And thus the ymage of my ſoule is defauted &amp; made foule i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſyght and is depreued thy grete vertues where by it ſholde be made fayre and acceptable to the what ſhall I do than but tourne me to the &amp; aſke mercy for that I haue ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed my lyfe ſo myſerably. A than I maye calle my ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le a ſynfull ſoule whiche is without drede of the &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſhame of ſynne vnderſtandynge that after the ordre of thy ryghtwyſneſſe ſynne muſte haue ſorowe / than my ſoule ought to haue ſorowe / and al my lyfe ſholde he we pynge / &amp; who ſhal gyue teres ynough to myn eyen that I maye wepe ynough for my myſerable lyuynge / and lamente that I euer haue ſpent ſo myſerably my tyme which I can not now reuoke agayen / ne fruytfully reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence but by ſorowe for my ſynne. ¶ Alas I haue loſte the well of lyfe and of al true ſolace / and I haue delued in the olde ſtynkynge cyſterne of ſynne / and the deceyua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble water ther of whiche ſemeth in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> begy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge ſwete and delectable / &amp; now it is tourned in to bytterneſſe / ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynacyon / and grete ſorowe. ¶ O mooſt mercyfull lorde whiche arte the wel of pyte &amp; of grace frome who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the flode of celeſtyall glorye doth ſtreme vpon all the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly courte. Replenyſſhynge them with all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; delectacyons paſſynge y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> poſſybylyte of mannes
<pb facs="tcp:9557:6"/> thynkynge / gyue me good lorde in this vale of my ſerye for the glorye of thy name the ſpyryte of compunccyon that I may bytterly wepe for my ſynnes and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylegyate by thy grace neuer frome hens forward da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably to affend the. ¶ O merueylous god how myſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly is my ſoule / whiche only can not ſorowe accordyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to the greuous offences that it hath done in this ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe but alſo it is in maner benomen and deed / for it feleth not the grete gooſtly ſorowes that it hath / wherby excep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it haue helpe by meane of penaunce it ſhal be brough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to the bytter paynes of euerlaſtynge deth. A I may curſe ſynne the whiche hath brought me ſo ferre frome the good lord / and ſo ferre fro my ſelfe that I haue loſte my fely<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> quyckeneſſe of my ſpyryte / and the gooſtyly taſte of all ſprytuall pleaſure and delectacyons in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. ¶ A myſerable ſoule a ſynfull ſoule why arte thou ſo dulle &amp; ſo ſlowe to all good werkes whiche art to the pleaſure of god / and to thy perpetuall promocyon and endleſſe Ioye / perpetual blyſſe and hertely gladneſſe / why arte thou ſo prompte and ſo redy to all wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and al werkes of abhomynable ſynnes whiche are to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grete dyſpleaſure of almyghty god / and to thy gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te payne and ſorowe and dampnacyon bothe of ſoule &amp; of body. Why arte thou ſo oblyuyous and forgetfull of fruytfull &amp; vertuous doctryne / and ſo retenty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of euyll fpekynge and wordes Incytynge to ſynne. Woo woo mayſt thou be whiche leueſte the waye of vertue &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt the waye of hyces / leueſt the waye of ſaluacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and takeſt the waye of dampnacyon. Thou haſte lyfe and deth bothe layde before the / and whiche thou wylt thou mayſte choſe. Loueſt thou not lyfe / hateſt thou not deth loueſt thou not delectacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and pleaſure / hateſt not thou
<pb facs="tcp:9557:6"/> payne and ſorowe. Alas how vnhappy arte y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> than whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che choſeſt the waye of ſynne / the waye of deth / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> waye of payne &amp; endleſſe ſorowe / and wylfully leueſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> waye of vertue whiche ledeth to ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Ioye and endleſſe myrth with al y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> herte can thynke or deſyre conſolacyon. Thou rennes to bodely deth &amp; not only bodely wherby thy ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſhall be departed frome thy body / but alſo the gooſtly ſyght of deth where y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt be for euer departed frome the face and clere vyſyon of god whiche is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyfe to thy ſoule lyke as thy ſoule is lyfe to thy body / the paynes of fyre and the terryble ſyght of the deuylles ſhall not be ſo greuous vnto the / as the ſondrynge frome thy lord god whiche full ſure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou ſhalte ſe hym in his glorye. Wold not thou ſaye that ſuche a man were worthy ſorowe and payne whiche wolde choſe to go that way were it neuer ſo pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there he knewe certaynly / yf he contynued therin that he ſhal be taken with theues robbed and put to the mooſt byttereſt payne of deth. Then I counſeyll the by tymes leue the waye of ſynne / for the ende therof is endleſſe ſorowe / and the pleaſure y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> cometh therof be it neuer ſo grete it ſhall haſtly paſſe. And yf thou come to that ende thou ſhalt take thy leue alſo true as god is true frome all pleaſures without ende. Our lorde of his grete mercy offred to the eternall pleaſure for a ſhorte temporall payne ſuffred accordynge to the ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his wyl / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylt refuſe ſo grete a lucre for ſo lytel a pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment than thou arte an vnhappy marchaunt. Then yf thou wylt not folowe the wyll of god in ſuffry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of this payne / but wyll fulfyll thynowne wyll in takynge thy ſhorte &amp; ſynfull pleaſures of this lyfe / arte not thou than worthy / by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtwyſenes of god to loſe and be depry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of this perpetuall Ioye &amp; pleaſure y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt not reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably
<pb facs="tcp:9557:7"/> ſaye nay. For thou that wylt refuſe ſo ineſtyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Ioye for ſo lytell a pryce / than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſetteſt lytell ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by / &amp; in that thou dyſableſt thy ſelf to haue it. ¶ And of very equyte thou whiche wylfully and ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully forſakeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>nal ſaluacyon / thou deſerueſt by the ryghtwyſneſſe of god to haue eternall payne and dampnacyon. Then beholde vpon the ryght ſyde the mercy of god whiche is redy to gyue the perpetuall Ioye for a ſhorte vertuous payne. And beholde vpon the lyfte hande the ryghtwyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of god whiche ſhall gyue the eternall payne for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſynge of eternal Ioye whiche thou forſokeſt for a ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ful pleaſur / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beware what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dooſt / he of his gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te grace offereth the perpetuall Ioye. And yf thou wylt ſo lyghtly refuſe it / than he thryteth the with endeleſſe ſorowe and payne that thou mayſte not eſcape his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / choſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> now whether thou wylt for a lytel payne ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue endeleſſe pleaſure / or for a lytel ſymple ſolace haue en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deleſſe pay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and ſorowe / and one thou muſte nedes cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. I counſeyll the to take payne and leue pleaſure / dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the to the ryght hande that thou be not founde at the daye of dome amonge the damned people vpon the lyfte hande / leue vayne and ſynfull temporall Ioye for the ende therof is ſorowe / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> lyueſt after thy pſelaunt deſyres of thy fleſſhe it ſhall brynge the to endeleſſe and paynfull dethe / yf thy fleſſhe lyue after thy ſoule / and thy ſoule after god / than thou ſhalt lyue eternally. ¶ A my ſeke vnſtable ſoule / dulle ſoule / myſerable &amp; ſynfull ſoule / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wold haue helth / ſtrength / loue / &amp; power: thou wold be moche made of / &amp; haue rycheſſe / fredom &amp; fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wolde be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out fere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out heuyneſſe / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wolde be ſwyfte / lyght / ympoſſyble / why ſekeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> the goddes in the regyon of dethe they are not here they are only there
<pb facs="tcp:9557:7"/> where is very lyfe / and no lyfe may be called very lyfe but only that lyfe whiche is eternall lyfe / for there deth hath no power ony thynge to mynyſſhe thy lyfe or ony thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> apperteyneth to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyfe / for frome y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyfe dethe is perpetuelly exyled whiche maketh this lyfe no lyfe / and all thynge to vanyſſhe awaye whiche perteyneth to this lyfe. ¶ A my ſoule loue that lyfe &amp; that lorde aboue all thynge whiche ſhall gyue the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ioyful lyf that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed lyfe perdurable and eternal lyuynge what haſt thou in this mortal lyf but laboure weryneſſe ſorow and pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / with theſe thou begynneſt lyfe / w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynueſt thy lyfe / with theſe thou ſhalt ende thy lyfe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pleaſures are ſhortly paſſynge / the ſorowes and paynes are longe abydynge / and all erthly Ioyes are medled with my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye of ſynne / thou thynkeſt ſynne is but lytell / wolde god thou woldeſt call it to mynde how greuous it is in the ſyght of the grete Iuge of the worlde a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> myghty god remembre how greuouſly he hath punyſſhed ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te parte of the aungelles he caſte out of heuen for ſynne whiche are of all creatures mooſt excellent in naturall perfeccyon. ¶ O how ſhalt thou thynke tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he ſhal ſpare the whiche arte ſynfull / for thou arte no thynge ſo precyous i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature as the leeſt aungell whiche was loſte and dampned for ſynne / &amp; thy body is but a dounghylle and a ſacke of ſtynkynge myſte / than truſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> that yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wylt not leue ſynne thou ſhalte peryſſhe with them / for the ryghtwyſneſſe of god wyll punyſſhe ſynne / &amp; ryght they ſhall peryſſhe frome y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> perpetual pleaſure &amp; glorye of god whiche wyll not leue ſynne / all we are exyled fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me paradyſe for ſynne / all the worlde was drowned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte .viii. perſones in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyme of Noes floode for ſynne the fyue cytees of whiche one was Sodome &amp; Gomorre
<pb facs="tcp:9557:8"/> were diſtroyed with fyre and brymſtone &amp; ſanke downe for ſynne / the Egipcyans were drowned in the rede ſee for ſynne / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren of Iſrael were kylled a grete nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre in deſerte for ſynne / &amp; now all the .xii. trybus are in captyuyte for ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / tranſlacyons of kyngdomes &amp; Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyres fro man to man is for ſynne / batayles / peſtylen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / and hungre in comyn plages of god contynually in ſome parte of the worlde or vpon the people is for ſynne and fynally all deſyre of ſynne ſhall ceaſe frome all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and tourne to vnremedyable paynes and ſynners ſhall be put with ſynners in euerlaſtynge woo there as they ſhal neuer tourne to Ioy or pleaſure agayne. ¶ A wretched ſoule why ſoroweſt not thou for ſynne / ſeeſte thou not how my lorde loued the and hated ſynne whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wolde ſuffre the mooſt paynfull deth to delyuer the frome ſynne / lerne to loue thy louer but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hateſt thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer / for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doeſte ſyu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e thou doeſte playnely that is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make hym to ſuffre deth agayne thou loueſt ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e whiche is the mooſt greteſt enemy for it ſhal brynge the except thou leue it to endleſſe &amp; horryble payne thou ſet teſt lytell by ſynne a wolde god our lorde myght ſet ſo ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell ther by / for than y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſholde be delyuered frome grete fereheuyneſſe &amp; payne whiche y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte deſerued for ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e but wo ſholde I be good lorde for euery tranſgreſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement for yf there come none other therof dyſobedyence it dyſhonoured the / a how ſholde I ſaye that ſynne is lytell for I can not truely ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the dyſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is lytell / a how I bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to honour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> deſyreſt it not for al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte done to me but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhold honour do to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. I receyue thy benefetes &amp; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſt no thynge recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of me but honour / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> gyueſt my goodneſſe &amp; this may growe. I may gyue to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> no goodes wherby y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> mayſte
<pb facs="tcp:9557:8"/> be the better for my goodneſſe may not growe. I maye gyue to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> honour &amp; this may not growe in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> but in me / &amp; whan thyn honour groweth in me than thy goodneſſe in me / &amp; al the prouffytes of my dydes in to me and none to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / for I may by dydes no thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> to better / but I may make me y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> better by thy grace i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I do honour to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. A dere lorde how wo ſholde I than be to diſhonour the / &amp; I may do no more dyſhonour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e whiche can not be done in mynde in wyll ne dyde but in the clere ſyght of the / a how woo ſholde I than be to do ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; ther by for to dyſhonoure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche arte my lorde and my god / my maker &amp; my redemer &amp; preſeruer / and fynally wolde bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge me to ſe thy glorye &amp; to haue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the honour in eternyte. A how ſhall I ſaye y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſynne is lytell ſythen y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e dyſhonoured y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> / &amp; no thynge ſholde be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſhamfull &amp; ſorowfull in me than for to do ony dyde to dyſhonoure the. Alas how may I fynde in my herte to to dyſhonoure y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whiche haue none helpe but only of the ¶ O wretched &amp; myſerable ſoule why remembreſt thou not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trouthe of god / for thou knoweſt it wel y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſyble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde make ony lye / &amp; thou knoweſte well that he promyſed no thynge but that it ſhal be fulfylled for the power is ſo grete that no thynge may lette hym / than thou knoweſt veryly that thou ſhalte appere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym and acompte all thy lyfe / and of all that thou haſte receyued of hym / what ſayeſt thou arte thou redy to thy rekenynge / canſte thou ſhewe that thou haſt wel expended and well vſed all the goodes that thou haſte receyued of god / haſte not thou vaynly loſte and vayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffred for to be loſte many of theſe gyftes of our lorde god / and many thou haſte expended that thou haſte
<pb facs="tcp:9557:9"/> to reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to laye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the at thyn acompte but that thou arte worthy to be dampned for them. ¶ Alas ſythe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou canſte not gyue a good rekenynge of thy tyme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended / why wylt not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> amende the / &amp; by the wyl ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of thy lyfe to come for to procure the fauoure of this ryghtwyſe Iuge / he is redy of his ryght grete mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to take one daye well ſpended for a yere. ¶ O than ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then he is thus kynde to the &amp; thou wylt contynue in vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kynde vnto hym / this ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of vnkyndeneſſe &amp; ingraty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude / yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt none other ſynne it is ynough to procure the Ire or wrath of this Iuge / why wylt thou than vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde ſoule dayly multyply newe offenſes why remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſt not y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grete Ieopardy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſtandeſt in for thyne olde ſynne. ¶ O wretche lerne to wepe applye &amp; to take wylful ſorowe / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moche cauſe haſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> to wepe and to ſoro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we / for yf y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> myght wepe as moche water as is in the ſee yet it were of thy ſelfe ſuffycye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te to waſſhe thy ſoule fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſynne y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dooſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as a malefactour whiche hathe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his prynce &amp; is ſory for to be taken &amp; to ſuffre grete payne / &amp; yet wylfully he wyll more outrageouſly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hym knowynge well that he ſhall ſuffre therfore the more payne / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſayſt to me that this prynce is mercyfull. I ſaye to the that he is mercyful to none but to ſuche as haue mercy vpon them ſelfe &amp; wyll leue theyr wretched lyuynge / than haue mercy vpon thy ſelfe and leue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye of ſynne / for thou ſhalte be called ſoner than thou truſteſt to thy acompte of all thy werkes of all thy ydel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of all thy wordes / of all thy ſylence / of all thy ſlepyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / of all thy wakynge / of all thy ſekeneſſe / of al thy hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the / of all thy rycheſſe / of all thy pouerte / of all thy fedyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / of all abſtynences / and of all thynge that thou haſte done and lefte vndone to the leeſt thought of thy ſoule / 
<pb facs="tcp:9557:9"/> and of al thynge perteynynge to thy power whiche thou haſte not ordeyned to the wyll of god &amp; ſaluacyon of thy ſoule / and thy body ſhall be punyſſhed with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> for it ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the and thou in it for the cauſe of ſynne is in it and it ſhall haue no payne but for the / for it myght not ſynne but by the. Alas why wylt not thou ſee whether thou goeſt &amp; beholde y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ende of thy paſſage that thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt that thou goeſt to pleaſures / &amp; as a blyndfull man thou goeſt euen contrarye towarde payne / thou thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou goeſt for to haue thy wyll / and thou goeſt there thou ſhalt haue all thynge contrarye to thy wyll / and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deſyreſt myrth and thou takeſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> waye of endles labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; perpetuall payne &amp; euerlaſtynge dampnacyon.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Edet ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>am mea. n vite mee. ¶ A my ſoule hath a grete cauſe to be wery of my lyfe / for I lyue not as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> louer of god ſholde lyue / but as a wretched catyfe whiche forgeteth god / &amp; deſerued to be forgote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hym. ¶ I haue no mynde vpon my ſaluacyon / my mynde is rather vpon thynge of dampnacyon. I endure me not to form me. I laboure not to repreſſe the wretched mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon whiche I fele in me. I ſuffre my mynde at large to renne in vanytees / as a creature that hath no god or Iuge ne thynge to anſwere for / ne thynge to ſorowe for ne to fere / for helpe is offred to me and I wyll not aſke it / it is offred to me and I wyll not put my hande ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to myn enemyes &amp; myn accuſers I conſente to / &amp; to my lorde &amp; my louer I wyll not conſent. A good lorde what ſhall I do at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dredefull day of deth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terryble dome in the day of Iugement. ¶ A how many thouſande ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall come tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prouyſyon as they laye in watche to take me whiche I ſee not now / &amp; I to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb facs="tcp:9557:10"/> no kepe to delyuer myſelfe by playne confeſſyon and many a thynge whiche I truſte now is no ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſhall tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appere greuous ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / and many a deed whiche I truſt now is good / than I ſhall fynde them euyl &amp; blacke and abhomynable they y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhal appere to me / there I ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue in ſoule &amp; body moche woo as I haue done in ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le and body moche wretchedneſſe / &amp; than ſhall I be w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for I ſhal receyue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> woful and ſorowfull endleſſe payne whan the tyme ſhall be paſſed except I leue now ſynne and torne me to god and deſerue by vertuous lyuynge to haue mercy / there ſhal be payne vnprofytable and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fruytfull penaunce / for that payne ſhall not remeue the ſynne of them whiche in this lyfe wolde not take wylful payne to be delyuered frome ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and able to be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from grace that they ſhall haue no power to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and to ſatyſfye for theyr offences / for whan grace was offred to them they refuſed it / and whan the tyme of penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was layed afore them / vnfruytfully &amp; necly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently they paſſed it. ¶ O good lorde now I ought for to remembre what I haue done and what that I haue deſerued to receyue for my doynge / all my yeres I ſhold recorde in the bytterneſſe of my ſoule / &amp; ſaye how my ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is conſumed without profyte / &amp; what woo I haue wrought to myſelfe / yf I coude remembre that I had done many good thynges than I ſholde be gladde / but I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue done many wretched &amp; euyl thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and fewe good / &amp; therfore I haue grete cauſe to be woo / &amp; yf I wyll not applye me to be wo where I ſhall be woo there I ſhal neuer departe therfro. ¶ A wo wo be to this grete hardeneſſe of myn hert / for theſe grete hamers of remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of eternall tormentes &amp; mooſt ſorowfull vyces are to lyght to breke it. ¶ O dulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:9557:10"/> inſanable and vnable to be heled all this ſharpe braydes are not ſuffycyent to quycken y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> / they are all to blunt for the. ¶ Alas ſythen the grete paynes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> god hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for ſynne are to lytel to put the in fere / and make the to be dylygent for thy ſaluacyon. ¶ A god mercy / a ded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dulneſſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is in me ſythen the terryble thondre of my ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp; ghoſtly ſyght of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grete abhomynable multytu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of paynes cauſeth no quyckenes of deuocyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / no my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerye of teres / no fere of god in me. ¶ A wo may I be whiche fele myſelfe in this grete myſerye / not redy to aryſe but rather deſyred to fall deper. I am worſe than a ſtone / for it is deſcended of nature for to deſcende / but I deſcende by malyce agaynſt nature. ¶ A de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lorde I loue more erthly vanyte than I do y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> or the place of thy glorye / my ſoule is croked al downe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erthe / for there y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loue is of the ther it is fyxed and not vpon y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it loked not vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> / here is mater of myſerye in me to exyte an hondreth ſoules to ſorowe &amp; make them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynue vneaſely in wepynge but my ſoule is ſo dryed fro al moyſture &amp; grace y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there cometh no teres fro me and thus I maye ſe myſelfe a drye ſtocke / a ſeer tree redy to fyre. A merueylous god how am I comen to this dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to this dryeneſſe / to this blyndneſſe &amp; derkeneſſe of my ſoule / my ſoule is made bynome &amp; Impotente to all perfyte dedes of vertue / &amp; not only it wanted wyll / but in maner it wanteth power to do well / &amp; what hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de me this febleneſſe but only ſynne &amp; what hath made in me ſuche ſynne but only a croked and frowarde wyll. A wretched dyſpoſycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my ſoule of the whiche I am cauſe myſelfe / &amp; therfore myn Impotenſy / &amp; Indiſpoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon to holy &amp; perfyte lyuynge is none excuſe to me / for this myſelfe hath made me by longe cuſtome in lyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb facs="tcp:9557:11"/> ¶ A good lorde an vnkynde ſoule am I to the. I can not dyſſymyle to the / for no thynge I may withdrawe from the ſyght of the / of a chylde thou haſt gyuen me power to lyue vertuouſly and to pleaſe the not for thyn auayle but for myn auayle for the endleſſe promocyon &amp; Ioye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reward to be receyued of the / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte called me / and yet y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> contynueſt it by good thoughtes / by good counſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le / by holy prechynges / by vertuous examples / by gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te gyftes / callynge to me for to come to the. And I as a wretche repell the &amp; all the gyftes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thou gyueſt me I abuſe to the dyſpleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> and to the grete accuſacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and without thy mercy to the grete dampnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of me I deſyre ſodayne ſorowes and paynes to come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me there thou haſte gyuen to me this reſpyte &amp; tyme of gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te delyberacyon to auoyde the paynful doungen of helle and to come to the Ioyfull Empyre of thy glorye there euerlaſtyngely for to dwell with the I attende it not wherfore I deſerue haſtely for to be caſte downe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynfull blaſtes of the grete horryble tempeſtes of deth. I knowe wel y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I may not here alwaye abyde / &amp; yet my mynde / and my loue is more here than there y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I muſte alwaye abyde. ¶ A merueylous god a grete blyndneſſe is in me that I ſholde deſyre for to abyde in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of myſerye there as I wel knowe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I may not abyde than for to be in the place of blyſſe and of myrth and gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te felycyte there as I may come yf I wyll and for euer abyde / god hathe made me a reaſonable creature for to choſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> beſte lyfe / and I make myſelfe an vnreaſonable creature for to choſe the worſte lyfe / &amp; I loue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I ſholde not loue / and I hate that I ſholde loue / and thus both my mynde &amp; my wyl I abuſe vnto my grete hurte whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thou haſte gyuen me to myn helpe / yf I ſhold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne
<pb facs="tcp:9557:11"/> vpon myſelfe all that I can reduce to my myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of myne owne wretchedneſſe &amp; vnkyndneſſe to god / remembry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the grete benefeytes &amp; gyftes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of hym / and how gentyll a lorde he hath ben to me without my deſeruynge certaynly all the wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacyon &amp; that I can ſaye of myſelfe is to lytell in regarde of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> grete dyſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacyon and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me whiche I haue deſerued / my wretched dyſpoſycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is more redy to do euyll than my memorye &amp; many moo yf they were knytte togyder with me are able to recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. I fele myſelfe full of wretchedneſſe. I am prone and all redy to all euyll / elles dulle &amp; ſlowe to all goodneſſe A ſythen I myght here or ſee my defautes ſhewed afore me lyke as thy be I ſhold abhorte with myſelfe lyke as with a toode or a ſerpent. A what drede ſholde my herte vnbrace of that terryble Iugement whiche muſt be gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen of myſelfe at the houre of deth where y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mooſt ryght wyſe Iuge hymſelfe ſhall accuſe me / &amp; myn owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence ſhal wytneſſe agaynſt me how I haue myſuſed my ſoule and lytel heded the valoure therof whiche was bought with the precyouſe blood of cryſte very god and man creatour and maker of the vnyuerſal worlde lorde of heuen and erthe to whoſe name all creatures ſhal do obedyence. I ſhal gyue accomptes how I haue abuſed my mynde my wyll my body all my fyue wyttes my ton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge my beaute my helth my ſtrength connynge vertue / how I haue myſordred myſelfe my ſoule and body the euyll mocyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s both of ſoule and body how I haue not done y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> was in me to repreſſe them but rather to kepe / them &amp; to werke them. All theſe good lorde I forgete &amp; of all theſe I ſhall gyue a ſtrayte accomptes. Alſo of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; drynke / golde ſyluer &amp; clothes / &amp; of all theſe whiche
<pb facs="tcp:9557:12"/> had ben vnder my tuycion / as chyldren ſeruauntes / &amp; of the euyll dedes that I haue done / and of all the good dedes whiche I myght haue done / &amp; for ſlouth &amp; ſlog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyſſhenes of myſelfe I haue lefte them vndone of al the tyme y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue receyued ſythe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had vſe of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ¶ A dere lord what ſhal I do at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> dredful houre of rekenyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge where as ſhall be ſhewed ryghtwyſneſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out grace yf I now laboure not for grace. ¶ O what ſhall I do drye tree that I am and brynge forth no good fruyte in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> chirche of god / but rather ſewed fruyte by many euyll wordes euyll werkes and euyll examples. I am an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proufytable tree apte &amp; worthy to be caſte in to endeleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe fyre. ¶ A what ſhall I do that daye whan I ſhall gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue acompte of all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyme gyuen to me of our lorde how I haue ſpende it to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> honoure of hym. I may ſaye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge is myn owne for I muſt gyue a ſtrayte rekenyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of all that I haue. I am but as a bayly &amp; a mynyſtre vnder god and taken charge well to ſpende his goodes dere lorde gyue me grace amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge al temporal myrth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to remembre the bytterneſſe of the dredeful accompte that I may that day receyue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> kyngedome of endeleſſe Ioye and mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Edet animam meam vite mee. ¶ A dere lorde ſeynge the myſpendynge of my lyfe I am wery of my lyfe. I myſelfe am greuous to myſelfe my bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then is grete &amp; is lyght to my body / but it is heuy to my ſoule / it is ſo grete y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it is lyke to preſſe me downe from heuen vnto the pytte of hell excepte ſpecyall grace and helpe of my ſauyoure. ¶ O my mercyfull lorde ſende me teeres y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> may lament daye &amp; nyght my myſerable lyfe &amp; waſſhe awaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fylth of ſo longe gaderynge of my ſoule I am woo whan I remembre ſo longe as I haue ben
<pb facs="tcp:9557:12"/> in this lyfe &amp; ſo wretched / and my wretchednes dayly greueth me / my mynde is all occupyed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vanytees and my wyll in frowardneſſe / my mouth in ſhrewednes my body in ydelneſſe / &amp; my werkes in wretchednes. A who ſhal gyue to myn eyen a welle of teeres y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally wepe &amp; wayle my woful lyfe my neclygent lyfe / my vnwyſe &amp; folyſſhe lyfe. I lyue not as a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture oughte to lyue reformy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge my ſoule &amp; body and my werkes to my lorde whiche hath ordeyned me in this ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by my werkes well ordered to hym I ſhold come to his lyfe whiche lyfe onely ought to be called very lyfe / for that onely is lyfe whiche can not be ended by dethe &amp; not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe where we dayly renne to deth / &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lyfe onely is helth whiche can not be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſekeneſſe / &amp; that onely is Ioy whiche can not be Interrupted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſorowe and that only is perfyte blyſſe whiche can not be melde with myſerye of payne or ſynne. ¶ O y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> blynde aſſe why openſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not thyn eyen for to ſee the dyffrence bytwyxte lyfe &amp; deth / vertue / and vices / ſekeneſſe &amp; helth / felycyte myſerye / laboure thou wretche for to aryſe whiche lyeſt ouercharged with olde ſynnes / putte feere to feere / we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge to wepynge / excepte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> aplyeſt thyſelfe wylfully to ſorowe / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ryght wyſneſſe of god ſhall magre thyn he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de brynge the to ſorowe. A choſe than the leſſe ſorowe to auoyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſorowe / the temporall ſorowe to auoyed the eternall ſorowe. Remembreſt not thou y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he ſhall Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the whome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt made by many folde offences thyn aduerſarye / to whome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt done dyſpyte and rebuke brekynge his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement afore his owne face. ¶ A god mercy I ought to be ſory in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brynge his kynde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe to me and myne Ingratytude &amp; vnkyndeneſſe to hym / and the more kyndeneſſe he ſhewed to me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more
<pb facs="tcp:9557:13"/> kynde I ought for to be to hym / and more I am bounde by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lawe of kyndneſſe for to pleaſe hym / &amp; the more my ſynne is. Yf I dyſpleaſe hym awo ought I than to be for lyke as kyndeneſſe is dayly more and more / for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that he ſpared me the more kyndeneſſe he ſhewed vnto me / ſo by the cyrcumſtaunce of vnkyndeneſſe / the more greuous is the ſynne in me. what ſhall I ſaye to this Iuge ſythen y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> onely myn owne kyndeneſſe is able to conuycte me whiche ſo oftentymes calleth me for to amende my lyfe Inwardely Inſpyracyon / and many a thought y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whiche he putteth in my mynde contrarye vnto myn owne wretched dyſpoſycyon. And outwarde he called me by prechynge / and by moche good counſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge / by redynge / by example gyuy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of ſuche whiche hath leſſe wytte than I / leſſe power to good werkes than I / god hath gyuen to me more precyous gyftes &amp; helpe to do well / and yet I do worſe or not ſo well / am not I than worthy afore that ryghtwyſe Iuge to haue grete punyſſhement / he that is now mooſt pacyent to me yf I amende not my lyfe ſhall be mooſt felle / and angrye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me. ¶ And he whiche now is mooſt lyberall to me / than ſhall be mooſt harde to me / and he whiche now is mooſt meke to me than ſhal be mooſt felleſt / now mooſt mercyfull / than mooſt rygorous and ſtrayte in Iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / I may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lee this Iugement / alwaye I am and ſhall be vnder his hande. Now I am vnder the ryght hande of mercy / than ſhall I be vnder the heuy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of his ryghtwyſneſſe. woo es me woo is me who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me haue I offended / whome I haue not atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded / who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me I haue prouoked to be wroth with me. ¶ Alas wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched what haue I done. I haue dyſhonoured my lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de god. I haue prouoked almyȝty god to take vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:9557:13"/> on me yf his hande of mercy had not reteyned y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſwerde of vengeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I ſholde haue peryſſhed longe afore this for many tymes I haue deſerued dampnacyon / but vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to this tyme he hath deferred y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſentence / and euer aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth whan I amende and come to reconſylyacyon ¶. O wretched ſynner why remembre not I of this lyfe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne is and for the tyme of this lyfe the grete kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in god and gratytude / &amp; how after this lyfe none ſhall be taken to grace whiche wyll not amende in this tyme and ſpace. I byleue as I were inmortall. I fere not what ſhall falle / and myn olde lyfe cuſtomes hath ſo tyed me y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> without ſpecyall helpe of my lorde god I can not loſe me. Helpe me good lorde frome theſe da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers of dygnacyon &amp; wrath of theſe I am benomen / my power is nought without ſupportacyon &amp; helpe of thy mercy. ¶ A what anguyſſhe ſhall be in me yf I do ſo vnhappe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gyde me to ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terryble daye where he whiche hathe mooſt loued me / &amp; mooſt done and mooſt ſuffred for me ſhall accuſe me where he ſhall laye his wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des agaynſt me / his croſſe / his ſpere crowne of thornes ſhall teſtefye agaynſt me / my good au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gell whiche hath ſo holſomly at many tymes counſeylled me / &amp; I haue repelled &amp; lytell ſette by his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyl this he ſhall witneſſe agaynſt me / ll deuylles whiche haue tempted me to ſynne there ſhay<hi rend="sup">•</hi> accuſe me / and there reherſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wordes of my profeſſyon there ſhall he ſhewe openly all my ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es in what thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue ſynned / in what place &amp; tyme / &amp; how I dyd ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / and what thynge: not only that I haue done euyl but what good werkes that I haue lefte vndone whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I ought to haue. All the creatures of god of whome I haue receyued ony benefyte or profyte ſhall accuſe me / for thy haue ſerued me by cauſe I ſholde ſerue god
<pb facs="tcp:9557:14"/> and that I haue deceyued theym &amp; done y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> was in me to robbe theym of theyr labours / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> heuen / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth / the ſonne what mynde of man ſholde not drede this terryble Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement / who ſholde not drede y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> preſence of the eternall Iuge where all ſynnes ſhall be brought clerly in our ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght &amp; thoſe thynges whiche we dyd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be layde afore vs to our grete ſorowe confuſyon &amp; deteſtacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Iuge ſhal be aboue vs whole ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des we ſhall not eſcape / the helle vnder vs &amp; the fendes redy to drawe vs thyder / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuge angered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out forth / y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcyence bytynge &amp; tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynge withinforth / &amp; ſythen the ryghtwyſe man ſcarſely ſhall be ſaued / the wretched ſynner ſo vnbelapped with wretchedneſſe where ſhall become whom feere of dampnacyon &amp; remorſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhall ſhake &amp; make hym to cry for woo. A wo may I than be whiche haue ſo many maters in me to bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge me to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> woo / it ſhal be Impoſſyble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> daye to hyde me / &amp; it ſhall be to terryble &amp; ferefull that daye to ſhewe me / &amp; nedeſly I muſt appere / and by myſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ony pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatour and anſwere for all y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I haue done here / &amp; not onely for myn owne dedes but for all perteyny<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to my care &amp; Iuryſdyccyon where ony defaute hath ben there I ought to haue helpe. ¶ O how ſhall I anſwere for many whiche am not able to anſwere for myſelfe. O my charge is grete my remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is lytell / my harmes do multyplye &amp; I ſeke no helpe. I renne to deth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſpoſed / my mynde is not with me. I am not with my ſelfe. I ſeke more for your aduauntage than for myſelfe my burden I ſhall onely bere for myſelfe. Now myght I make it lyghter but I enlarge it &amp; make it heuyer my ſelfe / but now aryſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſynner &amp; ſee how woo is thy ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure Cryſt Iheſu / he is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe of god by whom
<pb facs="tcp:9557:14"/> thou arte redemed his merytes are ſuffycyent though y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es be neuer ſo greuous call for helpe &amp; thou ſhalt not be ſhent / leue thy ſynnes &amp; chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thyne entente &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to do well / chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge falſe pleaſures in to paynfull ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace &amp; in to ſorowe / loke vp &amp; diſpeyre not for thou ſhalt haue helpe ynough / truſte on hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dredeſt / leue thy ſynne &amp; flee to hym y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue ſocoure in al thy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / renne agayne to hym frome whome y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> haſte ron<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>en Crye vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inportunely whom y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte offended mooſt greuouſly / and of his grete mercy he may &amp; wyll of all other helpe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mooſt redely / &amp; meke ꝯfeſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excludeth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peracyon for ther ſhall none be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pned but only for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes not truly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed. I mene of ſuche whiche as haue receyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baptyſme of cryſte. A Iheſu for thy holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is as moche to ſay by Interpretacyon as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauyour of ſynners / by his medyacyon Iheſu y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> holy name be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refyed of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in ſauy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of a grete ſynner / whiche haue ben by preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous wyll dyſobedyent vnto Iheſu / forgete my pryde &amp; ordyne it not to deth / but waſſhe my ſoule frome ſynne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoſe ſtremes of the blood whiche ranne frome the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayne of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ryght ſyde. Now behold ſwete Iheſu w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyne eyen of pyte theſe ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ers whiche calleth that ſwete name that comfortable name of the / the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to ſynners of mooſt delectacyon / the name of blyſſed hope / the name of ſaluacyon / and conuerſacyon. What is Iheſu but oure ſauyoure and redemptour / wherfore Iheſus for thy bytter paſſyon be to me Iheſus / y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſte made me nowe ſaue me / thou haſte redemed me frome dampnacyon now delyuer me than of thy goodneſſe and now ſuftre not me to peryſſhe for my wretchednes / ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre not wretchednes to leſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyn Infynyte good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to me / take to the good lord y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whiche
<pb facs="tcp:9557:15"/> is thyn and remeue frome wretchedneſſe for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is myn. ¶ Now Iheſu / Iheſu haue mercy vpon me this tyme of mercyfulneſſe that I may eſcape the terryble Iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the tyme of ryghtwyſneſſe / take me good lorde in to thy large boſom of mercy it ſhall be not leſſe good lorde / for the more thou receyueſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more it is / than thy mercy is large ynough whatſoeuer we do amyſſe &amp; we calle hertely this boſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is than redy. Admytte vs mooſt louely Iheſu amonge the nombre of thyn electe chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that with them we maye euerlaſtyngly laude the / and our profyte fruycyon and glorye in the amonge all thoſe whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oue thy name Iheſu to whome be honoure and glorye by Infynyte duraco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of eternyte.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>¶ Here endeth a lamentable complay<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſoule ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wretched lyfe of the body.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Enprynted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don in Fleteſtrete at the ſygne of the ſonne / by wynkyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de worde.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>device of Wynkyn de Worde</figDesc>
                  <p>W C</p>
                  <head>Wykyn de Worde</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9557:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9557:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9557:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
